question from a
friend and he
says Buddhism aims for
nibana Liberation from rebirth
reincarnation but this strikes me as a
very Bleak Outlook as if life were
merely a burden to be
escaped before Noble Truths Define life
as suffering yet I see beauty in it they
don't actually but never mind suffering
is real but life but is life itself
suffering I even want to reincarnate I
want to be reborn that Buddhism seeks to
end this cycle I accept that craving
caes suffering and I appreciate much of
the Buddhist teaching but is buddhism's
perspective on life truly this Grim or
am I misunderstanding something
well I guess yes and no I suppose um but
yeah you could say it's Grim from the
point of view of
sensuality from the point of view of
alcoholic depriving him of alcohol it's
the grimmest experience you can
imagine but the question is now are you
self are you have enough self-awareness
to recognize that you're an
addict that's that's flying down the
mountain and he can't stop it has to end
in a crash a repeated crash or you have
enough self-awareness to recognize that
and realize oh yeah so I can't trust my
perspective so would you trust the
perspective of an
alcoholic telling you that alcohol is
actually great and there is no harm but
a mere thought of giving it up freaks
him out
completely so Buddhism does not seek to
end the world Buddhism seeks to end the
world for those who want to practice
it if you don't want to practice ice it
Buddhism will happily leave you alone
the actual Buddhism I mean the actual
Dharma is not for
you so now obviously this person has
some recognition of the Buddhist
teaching how accurate it is well
obviously not not very much
um but they really need to um they
really need to look even closer
even to the principles of Buddhism that
they seem to agree
with and check them whether they were
actually the principles that the Buddha
thought about or the principles of the
later Buddhism that was more concerned
about the world
and happiness and making it a better
place for old beings and whatnot that's
not what the was teaching well he he was
what was he was teaching just not going
about it in the same way he was went
about a very different way the greatest
thing you can do to a mankind is to
fully free yourself from Sam by becoming
an
arand that is the greatest contribution
that you can make and make factually an
actual factual Improvement to the
samsara being a better place to that
little extent that somebody's freed from
it so if they
reevaluate what they think the Buddha
was teaching especially things that they
think they agree with but then they
disagree with the major Outlook of be
free from the world and it's not worth I
want to be reborn and so on then they
get to see that basically they're
carrying a contradiction you can't be
possibly valuing freedom from desires
and and so on in the in a true manner
that the Buddha was teaching as if like
you know when the Buddha was presenting
freedom from sensuality he wasn't saying
like um oh it will make your sensual
experience better if you practice
restraint it will make you appreciate it
more it will it will make you um have a
greater perspective on the world he was
like no no no it will free you from that
which is factually suffering but you're
not recognizing
it so it's not going to the dhama will
not uh help you tolerate alcohol
better it will if you actually practice
it correctly the way it was intended it
will show you that your intox that your
um love of uh alcohol and love I love of
samsara in that simul that I gave uh you
want to be reborn you love the happiness
of Life comes out of the intoxication
from the alcohol from the
life and comes and is rooted that's
that's where your perspective comes from
comes from the fact that you're not that
you're intoxicated that you're not thinking
intoxicated that you're not thinking
clearly so if you practice the dhama
correctly it shows you that that which
you think happiness is sensuality the
world is factually burning embers that
are that are that are harming you
damaging you right there right right now
while you're engaged with them factually
but you don't see that because you're
drunk you're drunk on
life so that's why it's important as I
said to to to check your sources and the
ideas of the dharm where it comes from
and try and bring it down to the early
sutas at
least because see how easy it is to
carry these contradictions oh I value
life I value Sam and I value Buddhist
teaching and I'm doing
both that's impossible
if you think you can do it means because
you're not doing the Buddhist teaching
and as I said even people that didn't
manage to become arahants in their
lifetime and so on but practice rightly
it's only because they ran out of time
or they got complacent with the practice
but at no point would somebody who
practices rightly the Buddhist teaching
think that he can have both World
desires and freedom from
desires because once you see desires as
burning coals the mind will turn away
from it it will be impossible to want it
like the suas how they said it in the
same sense it will be impossible for you
to desire your own
vomit it will be impossible for a stone
broken into to be ever joined together
doesn't matter what you try to use or a
dry Leaf to become green it's
irreversible Freedom From Desire is
irreversible because um being affected
by
desire was rooted in a uh mistake
a a self-perpetuating
misperception of factually
unpleasant that's felt pleasantly
because you're drunk you removed the
intoxication factually unpleasant will
be felt unpleasantly and you don't need
to tell yourself oh now I I will say no
to these desires there will be no more
desires towards
it so yes Buddhism is very Bleak if
you're still
drunk if you're not drunk you realize
this is the only Health that can
actually be acquired everything else is
still within your addiction it's still
within a problem it's still within some
s it's still going to have only partial
limited and expiring results